<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-10-11T22:26:45-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Yuan (Emily) Xue</title><subtitle>Check out my blog. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflection Sutton Part4</title><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/11/reflection-sutton-part4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflection Sutton Part4" /><published>2025-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/11/reflection-sutton-part4</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/11/reflection-sutton-part4.html"><![CDATA[]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Part II — Goal and Acting</title><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/07/reflection-sutton-part2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Part II — Goal and Acting" /><published>2025-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/07/reflection-sutton-part2</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/07/reflection-sutton-part2.html"><![CDATA[<p>In <a href="#">Part I</a>, I explored the idea of a <em>world model</em> — how systems like large language models (LLMs) understand the world, and where that understanding falls short.<br />
In this second part, I turn to the other half of intelligence: <strong>acting toward a goal</strong>.<br />
Understanding describes the world; goals decide what to do in it.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="intelligence-requires-a-goal">Intelligence Requires a Goal</h3>

<p>As Richard Sutton reminds us, <em>“Intelligence is about achieving goals in the world.”</em><br />
A system can model the world endlessly, but without a purpose, its knowledge remains inert.<br />
Where Part I focused on learning the world’s dynamics, this part centers on <strong>learning to act</strong> — the bridge from prediction to decision.</p>

<p>In reinforcement learning (RL), this bridge is formalized through the <strong>Markov Decision Process (MDP)</strong>, defined by a tuple ( (S, A, P, R, \gamma) ):</p>
<ul>
  <li>( S ): states</li>
  <li>( A ): actions</li>
  <li>( P ): transition dynamics (the world model)</li>
  <li>( R ): reward function</li>
  <li>( \gamma ): discount factor for future rewards</li>
</ul>

<p>The world model tells us <em>what happens</em>; the reward tells us <em>what matters</em>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="from-dynamics-to-objective">From Dynamics to Objective</h3>

<p>Once we can model transitions ( f(s, a) \rightarrow (s’, r) ), we can define the agent’s objective:</p>

<p>[
J(\pi) = \mathbb{E}_{\pi}!\left[\sum_t \gamma^t r_t\right]
]</p>

<p>This objective expresses intelligence as <em>optimization through experience</em>.<br />
The agent learns a <strong>policy</strong> ( \pi(a|s) ) — a mapping from states to actions — that maximizes expected cumulative reward.</p>

<p>Two broad approaches emerge:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Model-based RL</strong>, which plans actions using an explicit world model.</li>
  <li><strong>Model-free RL</strong>, which learns directly from trial and error, without ever constructing the model explicitly.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="two-broad-approaches-to-rl">Two Broad Approaches to RL</h3>

<h4 id="value-based-approach"><strong>Value-Based Approach</strong></h4>

<p>Value-based methods estimate the long-term return of each state or action via a <strong>value function</strong> ( V(s) ) or <strong>action-value function</strong> ( Q(s, a) ).<br />
This estimation connects short-term decisions to long-term outcomes — a way to see beyond the immediate reward.<br />
Sutton’s <em>startup analogy</em> illustrates this: an early-stage company may take actions that lose money now, but yield value later.<br />
Without a sense of long-term value, intelligent action collapses into short-sighted imitation.</p>

<h4 id="policy-based-approach"><strong>Policy-Based Approach</strong></h4>

<p>Policy-based methods take a different route. Instead of estimating value first, they directly <strong>optimize the policy parameters</strong> to improve expected performance.<br />
This approach, known as <strong>policy gradient</strong>, adjusts the policy in proportion to the goodness of outcomes:</p>

<p>[
\nabla_\theta J(\pi_\theta) = \mathbb{E}!\left[\nabla_\theta \log \pi_\theta(a|s) \, Q^\pi(s,a)\right]
]</p>

<p>In Sutton’s interview, he put it simply:</p>
<blockquote>
  <p>“You act, you see what happens, and you change your behavior accordingly — not because someone told you what to do, but because the world responded.”</p>
</blockquote>

<p>This line captures the spirit of policy-based RL: intelligence as the art of adjusting to feedback, not imitating prescriptions.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="the-llm-analogy-policy-without-and-with-goals">The LLM Analogy: Policy Without and With Goals</h3>

<h4 id="pretraining-policy-from-imitation"><strong>Pretraining: Policy from Imitation</strong></h4>

<p>A pretrained LLM can be viewed as a <strong>policy</strong> ( \pi_\text{LLM}(a_t | s_t) ) that imitates human linguistic behavior.<br />
It generates the next token by predicting what <em>a human would likely say next</em>.<br />
This is statistical learning — powerful but passive.<br />
Such a model lacks goal-driven correction; it learns human <em>descriptions</em> of success, not the <em>experience</em> of success itself.</p>

<h4 id="post-training-policy-with-a-goal"><strong>Post-Training: Policy with a Goal</strong></h4>

<p>Post-training introduces goals through <strong>reinforcement learning</strong>.<br />
In <strong>RLHF (Reinforcement Learning from Human Feedback)</strong>, the goal is to align outputs with human preferences encoded in a reward model.<br />
In <strong>RLVR</strong> and related techniques, the objective becomes <em>task success</em> — e.g., solving a math problem or generating correct code.</p>

<p>These phases transform LLMs from pure imitators into systems that optimize for explicit outcomes.<br />
Yet the transformation is partial: the model learns within narrow, human-specified boundaries.<br />
It is still far from an open-ended learner that explores and redefines its goals through experience.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="open-reflections">Open Reflections</h3>

<h4 id="is-post-training-correction-enough"><strong>Is Post-Training Correction Enough?</strong></h4>

<p>RLHF and RLVR bring purpose, but within limited and static objectives.<br />
Recent work in RL emphasizes the importance of <strong>entropy</strong> — the capacity to keep exploring.<br />
High-entropy policies resist premature convergence, maintaining curiosity in uncertain environments.<br />
Perhaps the next leap for LLMs lies in <em>continual, on-policy interaction</em> with the world — learning not just from labeled feedback but from the consequences of their own actions.</p>

<h4 id="reasoning-as-exploration"><strong>Reasoning as Exploration</strong></h4>

<p>Reasoning models and <strong>Chain-of-Thought (CoT)</strong> prompting introduce implicit exploration.<br />
Each reasoning step expands the model’s internal trajectory beyond the training corpus, forming a kind of <em>mental simulation</em>.<br />
Inference-time scaling — generating multiple thought chains before selecting the best one — resembles <em>policy rollout and evaluation</em>.<br />
Could this process act as an internal feedback loop, a primitive form of on-policy learning?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="closing-thought">Closing Thought</h3>

<p>Understanding is half of intelligence; acting completes it.<br />
A world model provides <em>prediction</em>, but a goal gives <em>direction</em>.<br />
As Sutton has long argued, the essence of intelligence lies in the continual cycle of <strong>acting, observing, and adjusting</strong>.<br />
Only when knowledge and purpose form a closed loop can we say a system truly learns from the world — not just about it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LLM" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="Reinforcement Learning" /><category term="LLM" /><category term="AGI" /><category term="Sutton" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Part I — World Model and Understanding</title><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/06/reflection-sutton-part1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Part I — World Model and Understanding" /><published>2025-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-06T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/06/reflection-sutton-part1</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/06/reflection-sutton-part1.html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="suttons-view-lack-of-world-model-in-llms">Sutton’s View: Lack of World Model in LLMs</h3>

<p>Sutton begins with a simple observation: <strong>LLMs never experience the world.</strong> He argues that these systems <strong>lack a world model</strong> — a sense of cause and effect, surprise, and correction.<br />
Without it, they cannot truly understand.</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“They learn what people would say, not what would happen,” Sutton notes.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>Put in another way, an LLM is a <strong>statistical mirror</strong> of human linguistic behavior. It reflects how people describe reality, not how reality unfolds.</p>

<p>But this raises a question: if LLMs truly lack a model that connects actions to consequences — the essence of understanding — then how do they still appear to know? When we ask LLM with a promot, “If I touch a boiling pot, what will happen?” the model will respond, “you’ll likely burn your skin immediately.” How should we reconcile this ability to state consequences with Sutton’s claim that LLMs don’t possess a world model? Or put more simply — is the ability to describe a consequence through language good enough, or even equivalent, to understanding the consequence itself?</p>

<h3 id="what-is-a-world-model">What Is a World Model?</h3>

<p>To unpack Sutton’s view, we must first understand what a <em>world model</em> is, why it is central to intelligence, and how it can be built.</p>

<p>Let’s begin with its simplest and most fundamental form: the dynamics model in reinforcement learning — a predictive model that describes how states evolve in response to actions.</p>

<p>A dynamics model is a function, often written as $\hat{f}$, that predicts the next state $s_{t+1}$ and reward $r_t$ given the current state $s_t$ and action $a_t$:</p>

\[s_{t+1},\ r_t \approx \hat{f}(s_t, a_t)\]

<p>With such a model, an <strong>agent</strong> can predict possible outcomes before acting — an ability fundamental to planning and reasoning.
In reality, we rarely have direct access to the true state of the world. Instead, we rely on observations from various senses — vision, hearing, touch — to infer an internal representation of the hidden state. State transition is also stochastic, reflecting ambiguity in how actions affect future states. A conceptual <strong>world model</strong> can therefore be represented as:</p>

\[\begin{aligned}
s_t &amp;= g(o_t) &amp;&amp; \text{(state inference)} \\
s_{t+1} &amp;\sim P(s_{t+1} \mid s_t, a_t) &amp;&amp; \text{(stochastic transition)} \\
r_t &amp;= r(s_t, a_t) &amp;&amp; \text{(reward model)} \\
o_t &amp;\sim P(o_t \mid s_t) &amp;&amp; \text{(observation generation)}
\end{aligned}\]

<h3 id="how-a-world-model-should-be-built">How a World Model Should Be Built</h3>

<p>Building a world model involves three intertwined processes:</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Exploration</strong> — Gathering Experience</p>

    <p>To learn the dynamics of an environment, an agent must act within it. It explores different states and actions, collecting trajectories of experience:</p>

\[(s_t, a_t, r_t, s_{t+1})\]

    <p>These trajectories encode causal relationships — how actions lead to consequences — forming the empirical foundation of the model.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Perception</strong> — Interpreting Observations</p>

    <p>In most real-world settings, the true state $s_t$ is often hidden. Instead, the agent observes sensory inputs $o_t$ (images, sounds, text) and infer latent states:</p>

\[s_t \approx g(o_t)\]

    <p>Here, $g$ is a perceptual encoder that extracts task-relevant information from raw sensory data, transforming perception into internal understanding.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Learning</strong> - Modeling the Dynamics</p>

    <p>Finally, learning integrates exploration and perception into a coherent predictive framework. Given collected trajectories and inferred latent states, the agent learns a stochastic transition function that approximates how the world evolves:</p>

\[\hat{f}(s_t, a_t) \rightarrow (s_{t+1}, r_t)\]

    <p>This process typically involves representation learning (to encode  latent states), sequence modeling (to capture temporal dependencies), and probabilistic estimation (to handle ambiguity).</p>

    <p>With deep learning becoming the de facto approach for representation due to its expressive power, large neural networks now serve as the core mechanism for modeling dynamics. They are trained on sequences of state transitions as ground truth, where each step in the trajectory supervises the model to minimize prediction error between predicted and observed outcomes. Through this iterative process, the learned model captures both environmental regularities and stochastic variability — forming the foundation of world model learning.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="how-a-world-model-is-built-in-llms">How a World Model Is Built in LLMs</h3>

<p>Now, let’s turn to large language models (LLMs).
LLMs do not interact with the physical world directly. Instead, they learn from humans — observers and actors who have already explored the world and recorded their experiences as language. As shown in the diagram below, LLMs are trained on traces of human experience: vast text corpus that reflects how people perceive, reason about, and describe the world around them. Language serves as a powerful medium — distilling complex sensory, emotional, and causal interactions into symbols and sequences. Next-token prediction, the objective of pretraining, provides the concrete mechanism through which this learning occurs.</p>

<div class="mermaid">
graph TD
A[Human Interaction with the World] --&gt;|Trajectory| B[Experience Expressed in Language]
B --&gt;|Text Corpus| C[LLM Pretraining]
C --&gt;|Next-Token Prediction| D[LLM as Learned Model]
</div>

<h3 id="the-limitations-and-possible-paths-forward">The Limitations and Possible Paths Forward</h3>

<p>This process clearly introduces several fundamental limitations:</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>Limited Exploration:
The exploration originates from human experience, producing a narrow trajectory that reflects only a fraction of the world. The model cannot act or gather new evidence beyond what humans have already recorded.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Limited Perception and Representation:
LLMs perceive only text — a symbolic medium through which humans express sensory, visual, spatial, and auditory experiences. Inevitably, some information is lost or distorted in translation. This representational gap leads to incomplete or inaccurate estimates of the underlying state of the world.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Acknowledging these limitations, it is worth examining what learning truly means in this context — and whether next-token prediction provides a sufficient form of self-supervision and deep neural networks, serve as powerful function approximators, capable of capturing complex dependencies and representations at scale.</p>

<p>On this point, Ilya Sutskever — in his conversation with Dwarkesh Patel on <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yf1o0TQzry8&amp;t=1671s">The Dwarkesh Podcast</a></em> (OpenAI, 2024) — offered a particularly insightful perspective.<br />
He argued that large-scale next-token prediction is not a trivial task: to perform it well, a neural network must learn to <strong>compress information</strong> into efficient internal representations and to <strong>generalize from the collective knowledge encoded in language</strong>, effectively synthesizing what he calls a kind of <em>super-knowledge</em>.</p>

<p>On this point, Ilya Sutskever — in his conversation with Dwarkesh Patel (same Youtube Podcast) <em><a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Yf1o0TQzry8&amp;t=1671s">Why Next-Token Prediction Could Surpass Human Intelligence</a></em> — offered a particularly insightful perspective.</p>

<p>Sutskever views next-token prediction as a profoundly deep task that extends far beyond surface-level statistics:</p>

<blockquote>
  <p>“Predicting the next token well means that you understand the underlying reality that led to the creation of that token.” While the process is statistical, Sutskever notes that the compression required to perform it effectively forces the model to internalize what it is about the world that produces those statistics.</p>
</blockquote>

<p>If this interpretation holds, then approaches such as increasing the diversity of pretraining data through large-scale simulation environments or expanding perception through multimodal models become practical and valuable directions for advancing LLMs.</p>

<p>Still, exploration remains the hardest frontier — models continue to rely on fixed set of human-collected trajectories. True world modeling requires interactive systems that can act, observe, and revise their own understanding through experience.</p>

<p><strong>Continuous learning</strong> represents a promising direction — adapting models within real-world environments through domain-specific fine-tuning. Such post-training adaptation could mark a step toward bridging static knowledge and experiential learning.
This also raises a compelling question: if we place an LLM in a new environment after pretraining, how well could it explore within that domain and generate new representations grounded in its evolving experience?</p>

<p>Viewed from another angle, we might ask whether a complete world model is even necessary.
Humans themselves operate under incomplete world models — constrained by limited perception and biased exploration — yet still act intelligently. Thus, the question shifts from “Can LLMs learn the whole world?” to “Can they reason, act, and gather enough information to accomplish the task at hand?”</p>

<p>That brings us to the next part: Goal and Policy — where understanding meets action.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LLM" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="Reinforcement Learning" /><category term="LLM" /><category term="World Model" /><category term="Sutton" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Intro</title><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/05/reflection-sutton-intro.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Richard Sutton’s Interview: Intro" /><published>2025-10-05T00:17:56-07:00</published><updated>2025-10-05T00:17:56-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/05/reflection-sutton-intro</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/10/05/reflection-sutton-intro.html"><![CDATA[<p>I recently listened to <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=BF1aXbY0hS8">Richard Sutton’s interview on the <em>Dwarkesh Podcast</em></a>. Often called the father of reinforcement learning, Sutton spoke candidly about the limitations of large language models (LLMs), the importance of continual learning, and his lifelong conviction that true intelligence arises from experience—not imitation.</p>

<p>For me, the conversation was both intellectually dense and personally inspiring.</p>

<p>Sutton’s interview raised questions that reach beyond algorithms and touch on the philosophical core of modern AI research and the practical of LLM in support Agent develpment via reasoning.</p>

<p>As I listened, a few themes stood out.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="1-is-next-token-prediction-a-fundamental-limitationor-an-efficient-way-to-compress-knowledge">1. Is next-token prediction a fundamental limitation—or an efficient way to compress knowledge?</h3>

<p>The term <em>LLM</em> has become a kind of shorthand.<br />
Pretraining is indeed next-token prediction—but post-training introduces reinforcement learning from human or verifier feedback (RLHF, RLVF), injecting goals, preferences, and interaction loops.<br />
Are these systems still “just predicting the next word,” or have they quietly evolved beyond that description?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="2-is-the-issue-about-when-learning-happensduring-training-or-after-deployment">2. Is the issue about <strong>when</strong> learning happens—during training or after deployment?</h3>

<p>Sutton often emphasizes continual learning: the ability to adapt through experience after deployment.<br />
Most models today are fixed—trained once, deployed behind APIs, and updated in large batches.<br />
But that boundary is softening.<br />
Techniques like reinforcement fine-tuning based on customer objectives, Cursor’s online RL tuning, and adaptive personalization models hint at systems that can keep learning safely in the wild.<br />
If models could adapt continuously after deployment, would that address Sutton’s critique?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="3-is-the-problem-one-of-modalitytext-versus-multi-modality">3. Is the problem one of modality—text versus multi-modality?</h3>

<p>LLMs began in text, yet they sparked the broader generative wave: diffusion models for vision, multimodal architectures like Gemini and Claude 3, and DeepMind’s <em>Genie 3</em>, a video-based world model that predicts and controls future frames.<br />
When video data provides sequences of passive perception and reaction, can we learn a world model from it—without explicit interaction or embodied experience?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="4-scaling-experience-can-abstraction-replace-direct-interaction">4. Scaling experience: Can abstraction replace direct interaction?</h3>

<p>The world is vast. Even humans, unlike squirrels, cannot experience everything firsthand.<br />
Language became our bridge—allowing us to share abstract concepts and accumulated knowledge across generations.<br />
If <em>experience</em> is the right paradigm, how can we scale it to the richness of human understanding without millions of years of simulation?<br />
And if <em>language abstraction</em> is not the answer, how can we enable scalable experience—and ensure that learned world models are passed on and inherited?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="5-can-a-system-learn-through-cultural-feedback-as-humans-do">5. Can a system learn through <strong>cultural feedback</strong>, as humans do?</h3>

<p>(Here, I turn to Joseph Henrich and Yuval Harari for insight.)<br />
Humans learn not only through direct reinforcement but also through the social feedback loops of culture—stories, norms, and shared values.<br />
Could an LLM, trained on human language and behavior, serve as a foundation for this kind of cultural learning?</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="6-the-value-of-imitation">6. The Value of Imitation</h3>

<p>Each of these questions sits at the edge of what LLMs <em>are</em> and what true intelligence might <em>require</em>.<br />
They prompted me to reflect on past insights from many great minds:<br />
Ilya Sutskever’s optimism about scaling, Geoff Hinton’s biologically inspired view of learning, Yann LeCun’s vision of world models, and Demis Hassabis’s synthesis of agents, planning, and memory.</p>

<p>Together, these perspectives trace a continuum of thought about what it means to learn and to be intelligent.</p>

<p>This blog series is my attempt to connect those threads—<br />
to see how these ideas align, diverge, and evolve—<br />
and to ask whether, by organizing our questions clearly,<br />
we might reason a little better together.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LLM" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="AGI" /><category term="Reinforcement Learning" /><category term="LLM" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Demystifying Gradients</title><link href="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/09/20/demystify-gradients.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Demystifying Gradients" /><published>2025-09-20T00:17:56-07:00</published><updated>2025-09-20T00:17:56-07:00</updated><id>https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/09/20/demystify-gradients</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://yuanxue.github.io/2025/09/20/demystify-gradients.html"><![CDATA[<p>Gradients are at the core of training LLMs—or any neural network—powering each learning step. You’ve likely heard terms like <em>loss</em>, <em>backpropagation</em>, and <em>optimizers</em> in ML 101, and maybe even <em>vanishing</em> or <em>exploding</em> gradients. But what do these really mean—and how do you handle them in practice?</p>

<p>Whether you’re fine-tuning pre-trained models or training your own from scratch, understanding how gradients behave is essential—it can make or break your training.</p>

<p>This post dives deeper to demystify gradients, exploring:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>mathematical foundations</strong> of gradient computation</li>
  <li>How gradients relate to <strong>model design choices</strong> like residual connections and normalization</li>
  <li><strong>Practical techniques</strong> such as gradient clipping and monitoring gradient behavior during training</li>
</ul>

<p>These are skills every LLM practitioner needs.</p>

<h1 id="mathematical-definition-and-concepts">Mathematical Definition and Concepts</h1>

<p>At its core, a <strong>gradient</strong> is a vector that points in the direction of the steepest ascent of a function. In the context of neural networks, we’re typically interested in the gradient of the <strong>loss function</strong> with respect to the model’s parameters. This gradient tells us how much to adjust each parameter to minimize the loss.</p>

<p><strong>Backpropagation</strong> is the algorithm used to efficiently compute these gradients. It’s essentially an application of the <strong>chain rule</strong> from calculus, propagating the error signal backward through the network from the output layer to the input layer.</p>

<p>We’ll delve into the analytical results of gradients in a simple neural network, illustrating how they are sensitive to both <strong>input data</strong> and <strong>network parameters</strong>. This sensitivity is crucial to understanding why gradients behave the way they do in deep architectures.</p>

<h3 id="-example-model-setup-a-simple-2-layer-mlp">🧠 Example Model Setup: A Simple 2-Layer MLP</h3>

<p>To build intuition, consider a very basic Multi-Layer Perceptron (MLP) with:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Input:</strong> $ \mathbf{x} = [x_1, x_2, \dots, x_D] $</li>
  <li><strong>Hidden Layer:</strong> 1 neuron with weights $ \mathbf{W}^{(1)} $, bias $ b^{(1)} $</li>
  <li><strong>Output Layer:</strong> 1 neuron with weights $ \mathbf{W}^{(2)} $, bias $ b^{(2)} $</li>
  <li><strong>Activation Function:</strong> Sigmoid function used in both layers:<br />
\(\sigma(z) = \frac{1}{1 + e^{-z}}\)</li>
  <li><strong>Loss Function:</strong> Mean Squared Error (MSE)<br />
\(L = \frac{1}{2}(y_{\text{pred}} - y_{\text{true}})^2\)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-forward-pass">🔁 Forward Pass</h3>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Hidden Layer:</strong>
\(z^{(1)} = \mathbf{W}^{(1)} \cdot \mathbf{x} + b^{(1)}, \quad a^{(1)} = \sigma(z^{(1)})\)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Output Layer:</strong>
\(z^{(2)} = \mathbf{W}^{(2)} \cdot a^{(1)} + b^{(2)}, \quad y_{\text{pred}} = a^{(2)}= \sigma(z^{(2)})\)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Loss:</strong>
\(L = \frac{1}{2}(y_{\text{pred}} - y_{\text{true}})^2\)</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="-backward-pass-computing-gradients-with-the-chain-rule">🔄 Backward Pass: Computing Gradients with the Chain Rule</h3>

<h4 id="️-the-chain-rule">⛓️ The Chain Rule</h4>

<p>In a deeper network, the gradient of the loss with respect to an early weight. In our 2-layer MLP, the loss depends on the first-layer weights through a chain of intermediate computations:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} =
\frac{\partial L}{\partial a^{(2)}} \cdot
\frac{\partial a^{(2)}}{\partial a^{(1)}} \cdot
\frac{\partial a^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}}\]

<p>Each term reflects:</p>

<ul>
  <li>How the loss changes with respect to the output layer activation $a^{(2)}$</li>
  <li>How the output activation depends on the hidden activation $a^{(1)}$</li>
  <li>How the hidden activation depends on the first-layer weights $\mathbf{W}^{(1)}$</li>
</ul>

<p>This sequence illustrates how gradients “flow backward” through the network using the chain rule. Let’s now zoom into each layer and examine the gradient computations in detail.</p>

<h4 id="output-layer-layer-2">Output Layer (Layer 2)</h4>

<p>We start by calculating the error at the output layer and then its gradients.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Error at Output ($\delta^{(2)}$)</strong>. This measures how much the loss changes with respect to the pre-activation ($z^{(2)}$) at the output layer.</li>
</ul>

\[\delta^{(2)} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial z^{(2)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial a^{(2)}} \cdot \frac{\partial a^{(2)}}{\partial z^{(2)}}\]

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Derivative of Loss w.r.t. Output Activation:</strong>
  For MSE, $\frac{\partial L}{\partial a^{(2)}} = (a^{(2)} - y_{\text{true}}) = (y_{\text{pred}} - y_{\text{true}})$</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Derivative of Output Activation w.r.t. Pre-activation:</strong>
  $\frac{\partial a^{(2)}}{\partial z^{(2)}} = \sigma’(z^{(2)})$</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Combining these, the error $\delta^{(2)}$ is:</p>

\[\delta^{(2)} = (y_{\text{pred}} - y_{\text{true}}) \cdot \sigma'(z^{(2)})\]

<ul>
  <li><strong>Gradients for Output Layer</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Now, we use $\delta^{(2)}$ to find the gradients for the weights and bias of the output layer.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gradient w.r.t. Output Weights ($\mathbf{W}^{(2)}$):</strong>
  \(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(2)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial z^{(2)}} \cdot \frac{\partial z^{(2)}}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(2)}} = \delta^{(2)} \cdot \mathbf{a}^{(1)}\)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gradient w.r.t. Output Bias ($b^{(2)}$):</strong>
  \(\frac{\partial L}{\partial b^{(2)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial z^{(2)}} \cdot \frac{\partial z^{(2)}}{\partial b^{(2)}} = \delta^{(2)} \cdot 1 = \delta^{(2)}\)</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h4 id="hidden-layer-layer-1">Hidden Layer (Layer 1)</h4>

<p>Next, we propagate the error backwards to the hidden layer.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Backpropagated Error ($\delta^{(1)}$)</strong> This calculates how much the loss changes with respect to the pre-activation ($\mathbf{z}^{(1)}$) in the hidden layer. It depends on the error from the next layer ($\delta^{(2)}$).</li>
</ul>

\[\delta^{(1)} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{a}^{(1)}} \cdot \frac{\partial \mathbf{a}^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}}\]

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Derivative of Loss w.r.t. Hidden Activation:</strong>
  This involves propagating the error from the output layer back through the weights:
  \(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{a}^{(1)}} = \mathbf{W}^{(2)T} \delta^{(2)}\)</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Derivative of Hidden Activation w.r.t. Pre-activation:</strong>
  $\frac{\partial \mathbf{a}^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}} = \sigma’(\mathbf{z}^{(1)})$ (element-wise)</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<p>Combining these, the error $\delta^{(1)}$ for the hidden layer is:</p>

\[\delta^{(1)} = (\mathbf{W}^{(2)T} \delta^{(2)}) \cdot \sigma'(\mathbf{z}^{(1)})\]

<ul>
  <li><strong>Gradients for Hidden Layer</strong></li>
</ul>

<p>Finally, we use $\delta^{(1)}$ to find the gradients for the weights and bias of the hidden layer.</p>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gradient w.r.t. Hidden Weights ($\mathbf{W}^{(1)}$):</strong>
  \(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}} \cdot \frac{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} = \delta^{(1)} \mathbf{x}^T\)
  <em>(This is the outer product of the error $\delta^{(1)}$ and the input $\mathbf{x}$.)</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p><strong>Gradient w.r.t. Hidden Bias ($b^{(1)}$):</strong>
  \(\frac{\partial L}{\partial b^{(1)}} = \frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}} \cdot \frac{\partial \mathbf{z}^{(1)}}{\partial b^{(1)}} = \delta^{(1)}\)</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h1 id="vanishing-gradients-and-exploding-gradients">Vanishing Gradients and Exploding Gradients</h1>

<p>Let’s revisit the gradient of the loss with respect to the first-layer weights in our 2-layer MLP:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} =
\frac{\partial L}{\partial y_{\text{pred}}} \cdot
\frac{\partial y_{\text{pred}}}{\partial a^{(1)}} \cdot
\frac{\partial a^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}}\]

<p>Each of these terms depends on:</p>

<ul>
  <li>The <strong>input data</strong> ( \mathbf{x} )</li>
  <li>The <strong>activation function derivative</strong> ( \sigma’(z) )</li>
  <li>The <strong>weight values</strong> at each layer</li>
</ul>

<p>Now imagine repeating this process for <strong>many layers</strong> in a deep network. The chain rule multiplies together one such term for every layer between the loss and the weights being updated. For example, in a deep feedforward network:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} = 
\left( \prod_{l=2}^{n} \frac{\partial a^{(l)}}{\partial a^{(l-1)}} \right)
\cdot \frac{\partial a^{(1)}}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}}\]

<p>This product of many terms is what makes gradients sensitive to <strong>activation function derivatives</strong>, <strong>weight magnitudes</strong>, and <strong>network depth</strong>.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="-vanishing-gradients">🧊 Vanishing Gradients</h3>

<p>If activation derivatives and weights are small (e.g., ( \sigma’(z) &lt; 1 )), the product shrinks exponentially:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \approx 0\]

<p>This leads to <strong>early layers receiving almost no gradient signal</strong>, and therefore learning very slowly or not at all.</p>

<p>This issue is especially problematic in:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Deep feedforward networks</li>
  <li>Recurrent neural networks (RNNs)</li>
  <li>Transformers with long dependency chains</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="-exploding-gradients">🔥 Exploding Gradients</h3>

<p>If activation derivatives or weights are too large (e.g., ( &gt; 1 )), the gradient can grow rapidly:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \gg 1\]

<p>This results in <strong>unstable training</strong>, where weight updates are excessively large, causing divergence or <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NaN</code> values in the loss.</p>

<hr />

<h3 id="-generalizing-the-problem">🧠 Generalizing the Problem</h3>

<p>These issues become more pronounced when:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Depth increases</strong>: More layers mean more multiplications of derivatives</li>
  <li><strong>Activation functions</strong> like sigmoid or tanh saturate (i.e., their derivatives approach 0)</li>
  <li><strong>Poor weight initialization</strong>: Large or small initial weights amplify the problem</li>
  <li><strong>Input scaling</strong> is inconsistent: Large or small feature values distort activation distributions</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="-why-it-matters">❗ Why It Matters</h3>

<p>Vanishing and exploding gradients can <strong>cripple training</strong>, especially in large-scale LLMs or deep vision models. Without mitigation, early layers fail to learn or cause instability, making convergence difficult or impossible.</p>

<hr />
<p>Gemini</p>

<p>As neural networks grow deeper, training them effectively becomes challenging due to two significant problems that arise during backpropagation: <strong>Vanishing Gradients</strong> and <strong>Exploding Gradients</strong>. These issues directly impact the learning process, particularly for the earlier layers of the network.</p>

<h2 id="the-core-problem-products-of-derivatives">The Core Problem: Products of Derivatives</h2>

<p>Recall our backpropagation derivation. The error term for a layer, $\delta^{(l)}$, is calculated by propagating the error from the subsequent layer, involving a product with that layer’s weights and the derivative of the current layer’s activation function:</p>

\[\delta^{(l)} = (\mathbf{W}^{(l+1)T} \delta^{(l+1)}) \odot \sigma'(\mathbf{z}^{(l)})\]

<p>When we calculate the gradient for the weights of an early layer, say $\mathbf{W}^{(1)}$, this process involves a chain of multiplications through all subsequent layers. For example, extending our 2-layer network to a 3-layer network, the error for the first hidden layer would involve terms from $\delta^{(2)}$ and $\mathbf{W}^{(2)}$ as shown above. If we had even more layers, say up to layer $N$, the error $\delta^{(1)}$ would effectively look something like this in a simplified chain rule expansion (ignoring biases and specific matrix operations for clarity):</p>

\[\delta^{(1)} \propto \delta^{(N)} \cdot (\mathbf{W}^{(N)}) \cdot \sigma'(\mathbf{z}^{(N-1)}) \cdot (\mathbf{W}^{(N-1)}) \cdot \sigma'(\mathbf{z}^{(N-2)}) \cdots (\mathbf{W}^{(2)}) \cdot \sigma'(\mathbf{z}^{(1)})\]

<p>This expression highlights a critical point: the error signal (and consequently the gradients) for earlier layers is a <strong>product of many terms</strong>, specifically the weights ($\mathbf{W}$) and the derivatives of the activation functions ($\sigma’(\mathbf{z})$) from all subsequent layers.</p>

<h3 id="vanishing-gradients">Vanishing Gradients</h3>

<p>If these individual terms, especially the activation function derivatives ($\sigma’(\mathbf{z})$) and the weights ($\mathbf{W}$), are predominantly <strong>less than 1</strong> (or 1 in magnitude), then the product of many such terms shrinks exponentially as we propagate backward through the layers.</p>

<p>For instance, consider $\sigma’(z)$ for a Sigmoid activation function. Its maximum value is $0.25$. If you multiply $0.25$ by itself many times (e.g., $0.25^5 = 0.000976$), the value quickly approaches zero.</p>

<p>This leads to:
\(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \to 0\)</p>

<p><strong>Impact:</strong> Gradients for the parameters in early layers become extremely small, close to zero. This means updates to these parameters are negligible, and these layers learn very slowly or effectively stop learning altogether. The network struggles to capture long-range dependencies in the data, as information from the output cannot effectively influence the initial feature extraction. This is a common challenge in deep Recurrent Neural Networks (RNNs) and very deep feedforward networks.</p>

<h3 id="exploding-gradients">Exploding Gradients</h3>

<p>Conversely, if the terms (weights and activation derivatives) are predominantly <strong>greater than 1</strong> (or 1 in magnitude), their product grows exponentially as we propagate backward.</p>

<p>This results in:
\(\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \gg 1\)</p>

<p><strong>Impact:</strong> Gradients become excessively large, leading to massive updates to the network parameters. This causes the training process to become unstable, leading to oscillations, <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NaN</code> (Not a Number) values in the loss, and ultimately preventing the model from converging.</p>

<h2 id="general-contributing-factors">General Contributing Factors</h2>

<p>Both vanishing and exploding gradients are exacerbated by several factors in deep networks:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Number of Layers (Network Depth):</strong> The deeper the network, the more multiplications are involved in the backpropagation chain, magnifying the effect of both small and large values.</li>
  <li><strong>Choice of Activation Function:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Sigmoid and Tanh:</strong> Their derivatives ($\sigma’(z)$) are always less than 1 (max $0.25$ for sigmoid, max $1$ for tanh), making them highly susceptible to vanishing gradients, especially in deep networks.</li>
      <li><strong>ReLU and its variants (Leaky ReLU, ELU):</strong> These functions have a derivative of 1 for positive inputs, which helps to mitigate vanishing gradients.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Weight Initialization:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Initializing weights too small can push activation outputs towards the flat regions of sigmoid/tanh, leading to small derivatives and vanishing gradients.</li>
      <li>Initializing weights too large can cause activations to become very large (or very small for sigmoid/tanh), again leading to small derivatives (flat regions) for sigmoid/tanh, or directly contributing to exploding gradients.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Nature of Data:</strong> While less direct, poorly scaled input data can lead to extreme $z$ values, pushing activations into problematic regions.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="mitigations-and-solutions">Mitigations and Solutions</h2>

<p>Fortunately, researchers have developed several techniques to combat vanishing and exploding gradients:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Activation Functions:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>ReLU (Rectified Linear Unit)</strong> and its variants (Leaky ReLU, ELU, SELU) are widely used as they have non-saturating gradients for positive inputs, effectively mitigating vanishing gradients.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Improved Weight Initialization:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Xavier/Glorot Initialization:</strong> Designed for sigmoid/tanh activations, it scales initial weights based on the number of input and output units to keep activations in a reasonable range.</li>
      <li><strong>He Initialization:</strong> Optimized for ReLU activations, it similarly scales weights to prevent gradients from vanishing or exploding.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Batch Normalization:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Normalizes the activations of each layer, maintaining them within a stable range. This helps prevent activations from falling into the saturated (flat gradient) regions of activation functions and also smooths the gradient flow, mitigating both vanishing and exploding gradients.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Gradient Clipping:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li>Specifically targets exploding gradients. If the L2 norm of the gradients exceeds a certain threshold, the gradients are scaled down. This prevents individual large gradients from destabilizing training.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li><strong>Network Architectures:</strong>
    <ul>
      <li><strong>Residual Connections (ResNets):</strong> Allow gradients to flow directly through “skip connections,” bypassing layers and ensuring a clear path for gradients to reach earlier layers, effectively combating vanishing gradients.</li>
      <li><strong>LSTMs and GRUs:</strong> These specialized recurrent neural network architectures were explicitly designed with internal “gates” that help maintain a constant error flow, largely solving the vanishing gradient problem in RNNs.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ul>

<h2 id="by-carefully-choosing-activation-functions-initializing-weights-employing-normalization-techniques-and-leveraging-advanced-architectures-we-can-successfully-train-very-deep-neural-networks-unlocking-their-immense-potential">By carefully choosing activation functions, initializing weights, employing normalization techniques, and leveraging advanced architectures, we can successfully train very deep neural networks, unlocking their immense potential.</h2>
<p>OLD….</p>

<p>If activation derivatives and weights are small (e.g., $ \sigma’(z) &lt; 1 $), the product of many such terms shrinks quickly:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \approx 0\]

<p>Early layers stop learning.</p>

<p>If derivatives or weights are large, the gradient grows exponentially:</p>

\[\frac{\partial L}{\partial \mathbf{W}^{(1)}} \gg 1\]

<p>Leads to unstable training and divergence.</p>

<p>As neural networks grow deeper, two significant problems can arise:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Vanishing Gradients:</strong> When gradients become extremely small during backpropagation, the updates to the parameters in the early layers of the network become negligible. This means these layers learn very slowly, or effectively stop learning altogether, hindering the model’s ability to capture long-range dependencies in the data. This is particularly problematic in recurrent neural networks (RNNs) and transformer models with many layers.</li>
  <li><strong>Exploding Gradients:</strong> Conversely, gradients can become excessively large, leading to massive updates to the network parameters. This can cause the model to diverge, making training unstable and preventing convergence. Exploding gradients often manifest as <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NaN</code> (Not a Number) values in the loss.</li>
</ul>

<p>Both phenomena can cripple the training process, making it difficult or impossible to achieve good performance.</p>

<h1 id="approaches-to-address-the-issues">Approaches to Address the Issues</h1>

<p>Fortunately, researchers have developed several effective techniques to mitigate vanishing and exploding gradients:</p>

<h2 id="normalization-dealing-with-inputs-and-activations-in-architecture-design">Normalization (Dealing with Inputs and Activations in Architecture Design)</h2>

<p>Normalization techniques aim to regularize the activations and inputs of neural networks, keeping them within a stable range.</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Batch Normalization:</strong> Normalizes the activations of a layer across a mini-batch, making training more stable and allowing for higher learning rates.</li>
  <li><strong>Layer Normalization:</strong> Normalizes the activations within each sample across all features, commonly used in transformer models.</li>
  <li><strong>Weight Normalization:</strong> Normalizes the weights of a layer, separating the magnitude from the direction.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="residual-connections">Residual Connections</h2>

<p><strong>Residual connections</strong> are a fundamental building block in deep neural networks, particularly Transformers (which LLMs are based on). They help mitigate vanishing and exploding gradients by providing a direct “shortcut” path for the gradient to flow through, preventing the gradient signal from becoming too small (vanishing) or too large (exploding) as it propagates backward through many layers.</p>

<p>Introduced in ResNet architectures, residual connections (or skip connections) allow gradients to flow directly through the network, bypassing non-linear activation functions. This provides a “shortcut” for the gradient signal, significantly alleviating the vanishing gradient problem in very deep networks.</p>

<h2 id="post-normalization-vs-pre-normalization-interaction-of-normalization-with-residuals">Post-Normalization vs. Pre-Normalization: Interaction of Normalization with Residuals</h2>

<p>The architecture of modern deep learning models, especially Large Language Models (LLMs), heavily relies on <strong>normalization layers</strong> and <strong>residual connections</strong>. A critical design choice that significantly impacts training stability and final model performance is where the normalization layer is placed relative to the residual connection and the main neural network operations (like self-attention or feed-forward networks). This decision often boils down to a debate between <strong>Post-Normalization</strong> and <strong>Pre-Normalization</strong>.</p>

<h3 id="post-normalization-post-ln">Post-Normalization (Post-LN)</h3>

<p><strong>Architecture:</strong> In Post-Normalization, the normalization layer is applied <em>after</em> the residual connection.
\(\text{output} = \text{LayerNorm}(\text{x} + \text{F}(\text{x}))\)
Here, $F(x)$ represents the main operation (e.g., a multi-head attention block or a feed-forward network), and $x$ is the input to the block, which is added back as a residual.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Stronger Regularization:</strong> Post-LN tends to provide stronger regularization effects. This often translates to better final model performance and generalization capabilities, as it helps prevent overfitting.</li>
  <li><strong>Larger Gradients in Deeper Layers:</strong> It can preserve larger gradient norms in deeper layers, allowing these layers to learn more effectively from the error signal.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Training Instability:</strong> Post-LN can be more difficult to train, especially in very deep models. This instability arises because the input to the normalization layer (the sum of <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">F(x)</code>) can have a very wide range of values, making it harder for the network to converge. It can also suffer from <strong>vanishing gradients</strong> in earlier layers.</li>
  <li><strong>Perturbation of Residual:</strong> The normalization operation applied <em>after</em> the residual addition can, in some cases, “distort” the direct flow of the residual signal. While the goal of the residual connection is to preserve the original signal (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code>), normalizing it afterward changes its scale and distribution. This might potentially make it harder for the network to rely on the clean identity path provided by the residual connection.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="pre-normalization-pre-ln">Pre-Normalization (Pre-LN)</h3>

<p><strong>Architecture:</strong> In Pre-Normalization, the normalization layer is applied <em>before</em> the main neural network operation, and then the residual connection adds the original input.
\(\text{output} = \text{x} + \text{F}(\text{LayerNorm}(\text{x}))\)
Here, $F$ operates on the normalized version of $x$, and the original $x$ is added back.</p>

<p><strong>Pros:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Improved Training Stability:</strong> Pre-LN generally leads to more stable training and faster convergence, especially in very deep networks. This is because the inputs to the attention and feed-forward layers are always normalized, providing a well-conditioned input that is easier for the network to process.</li>
  <li><strong>Prominent Identity Path:</strong> The identity path (the “x” in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x + F(LayerNorm(x))</code>) is more direct and less interfered with by normalization. This can be beneficial for consistent gradient flow, as the raw residual signal remains untouched.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>Cons:</strong></p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Suboptimal Performance/Generalization:</strong> While offering greater stability, Pre-LN often leads to slightly inferior final performance or generalization compared to Post-LN. This is hypothesized to be due to weaker regularization effects.</li>
  <li><strong>Diminished Gradients in Deeper Layers (for some architectures):</strong> Some research suggests that Pre-LN can lead to diminished gradient norms in its deeper layers under certain conditions, potentially reducing their learning effectiveness.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="why-post-normalization-could-interfere-with-residuals-and-why-its-a-trade-off">Why Post-Normalization Could Interfere with Residuals (and why it’s a trade-off)</h3>

<p>The term “interference” isn’t necessarily a fatal flaw but rather a design challenge. When normalization happens <em>after</em> the residual addition:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Direct Modification of the Identity Path:</strong> The original input <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> that is passed through the residual connection (<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x + F(x)</code>) is then immediately normalized. This means the identity signal <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> is no longer pristine; its scale and distribution are altered by the normalization. While normalization is beneficial overall, this direct modification of the very signal meant to be preserved can make it harder for the network to fully leverage the “identity mapping” property of residual connections, particularly at initialization.</li>
  <li><strong>Interaction with Activation Ranges:</strong> The sum <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x + F(x)</code> can have a very broad range of values before normalization. If <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">F(x)</code> produces very large or very small values, summing it with <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">x</code> can lead to an unstable input to the normalization layer, making training more challenging.</li>
  <li><strong>Impact on Gradient Flow:</strong> While residual connections are designed to improve gradient flow, normalizing <em>after</em> the addition can still influence how gradients propagate. The normalization step itself has learnable parameters, and its interaction with the summed signal can create complex gradient landscapes that are harder to navigate during optimization.</li>
</ul>

<hr />

<h3 id="current-trends-and-solutions">Current Trends and Solutions</h3>

<p>Despite the potential for training instability, <strong>Post-Normalization often yields better final performance in LLMs</strong>, especially in terms of generalization. This has led to its adoption in many successful transformer architectures. Researchers are constantly working on solutions to mitigate the training difficulties of Post-LN while retaining its performance benefits. These include:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Careful Initialization:</strong> Specific initialization strategies (e.g., using smaller initial weights or scaling factors) can help stabilize Post-LN training.</li>
  <li><strong>DeepNorm:</strong> This technique specifically addresses training instability in deep transformers by adaptively scaling residual connections, ensuring that the network’s activations and gradients remain within a manageable range.</li>
  <li><strong>HybridNorm/Mix-LN:</strong> These approaches combine Pre-Norm and Post-Norm strategies within the same model. For example, some models might use Post-Norm in earlier layers for performance and Pre-Norm in deeper layers for stability, or apply different normalization types within different sub-components of a block.</li>
  <li><strong>Adaptive Learning Rates and Optimizers:</strong> Using optimizers that are robust to noisy or unstable gradients (such as AdamW with careful learning rate scheduling) can also help to manage the challenges posed by Post-LN.</li>
</ul>

<p>In summary, post-normalization’s “interference” with residual connections isn’t that it breaks them, but rather that it modifies the identity path and can make training more challenging. However, the stronger regularization and improved generalization offered by post-normalization often make it a worthwhile trade-off, leading to superior final model performance in LLMs. The research community continues to explore ways to get the best of both worlds: stable training and high performance.</p>

<h2 id="gradient-clipping">Gradient Clipping</h2>

<p><strong>Gradient Clipping</strong> is a simple yet effective technique to combat exploding gradients. When the magnitude of the gradients exceeds a certain threshold, they are scaled down to prevent them from becoming too large. This ensures more stable updates to the model parameters.</p>

<h4 id="34-data-cleaning-and-preprocessing">3.4 Data Cleaning and Preprocessing</h4>

<p>While not directly a gradient-specific technique, high-quality, properly preprocessed data can significantly impact gradient stability. Outliers, inconsistent scaling, or noisy data can lead to erratic gradients. Thorough data cleaning and appropriate scaling/normalization of input features are fundamental to robust model training.</p>

<h1 id="hands-on">Hands-On</h1>

<p>Theory is great, but practical experience solidifies understanding. Let’s explore how to work with gradients in popular machine learning libraries.</p>

<h2 id="get-gradients-from-training-libraries-pytorch-tensorflow">Get Gradients from Training Libraries (PyTorch, TensorFlow)</h2>

<p>We’ll demonstrate how to access and inspect gradients in PyTorch and TensorFlow. Understanding how to query these values programmatically is the first step toward diagnosing gradient issues.</p>

<div class="language-python highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="c1"># Example in PyTorch (conceptual)
</span><span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">torch</span>
<span class="kn">import</span> <span class="n">torch.nn</span> <span class="k">as</span> <span class="n">nn</span>

<span class="c1"># Define a simple model
</span><span class="n">model</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">nn</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">Linear</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">loss_fn</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">nn</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">MSELoss</span><span class="p">()</span>
<span class="n">optimizer</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">torch</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">optim</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nc">SGD</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">model</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">parameters</span><span class="p">(),</span> <span class="n">lr</span><span class="o">=</span><span class="mf">0.01</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Dummy data
</span><span class="n">x</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">torch</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">randn</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">10</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">y_true</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="n">torch</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">randn</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="mi">1</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Forward pass
</span><span class="n">y_pred</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">model</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">x</span><span class="p">)</span>
<span class="n">loss</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="nf">loss_fn</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="n">y_pred</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">y_true</span><span class="p">)</span>

<span class="c1"># Backward pass to compute gradients
</span><span class="n">loss</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">backward</span><span class="p">()</span>

<span class="c1"># Access gradients
</span><span class="k">for</span> <span class="n">name</span><span class="p">,</span> <span class="n">param</span> <span class="ow">in</span> <span class="n">model</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">named_parameters</span><span class="p">():</span>
    <span class="k">if</span> <span class="n">param</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">grad</span> <span class="ow">is</span> <span class="ow">not</span> <span class="bp">None</span><span class="p">:</span>
        <span class="nf">print</span><span class="p">(</span><span class="sa">f</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="s">Gradient for </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">name</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="s">: </span><span class="si">{</span><span class="n">param</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="n">grad</span><span class="p">.</span><span class="nf">norm</span><span class="p">().</span><span class="nf">item</span><span class="p">()</span><span class="si">}</span><span class="sh">"</span><span class="p">)</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<h2 id="monitor-gradients-during-training-existing-metrics-and-logs-from-llm-training-libraries-eg-trl-vllm">Monitor Gradients During Training, Existing Metrics and Logs from LLM Training Libraries (e.g., TRL, VLLM)</h2>

<p>Modern LLM training frameworks often provide built-in mechanisms to monitor gradients. We’ll explore how to leverage these tools to observe gradient behavior during training. This includes looking at:</p>

<ul>
  <li><strong>Gradient Norm:</strong> The overall magnitude of gradients, which can indicate vanishing or exploding issues.</li>
  <li><strong>Per-Layer Gradient Norms:</strong> Observing if certain layers are experiencing more severe vanishing/exploding issues.</li>
  <li><strong>Histograms of Gradients:</strong> Visualizing the distribution of gradient values over time to identify problematic patterns.</li>
</ul>

<p>Just like life is a continuous hill-climbing journey towards your goals, gradients represent each strategic step. Happy <strong>gradient ascending!</strong></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="LLM" /><category term="AI" /><category term="Deep Learning" /><category term="Gradients" /><category term="Normalization" /><category term="Residuals" /><category term="Clipping" /></entry></feed>